Hi! Welcome back to Nagarjuna.
And we've reached the sixth class.
I'd like to show you a
picture which sums up
what we talked about last time.
And here you can see a
lady cleaning the floor.
And this comes from an
actual event at my house
where I kept walking out
into the kitchen at night
to get a glass of water or something,
and I would step in a puddle of water.
So turn on the light, get a cloth,
clean up the puddle of
water, get my glass of water,
go back to bed.
And this went on night after night.
And every night, I would
patiently get on my knees
and clean up the puddle of water.
And then finally after
about three weeks, I'm like,
"Hey, maybe it's coming from somewhere."
I was like, "Duh!"
And I looked under the sink.
I guess, subconsciously,
I really didn't want
to look under the sink
because it's so scary down there.
There's so much weird stuff down there
that I threw down there
and I didn't want to go through the sink
and find out everything was soaked.
But I did and it was.
The idea of Buddhism... it's very beautiful.
You don't attack the result,
you attack the cause.
So you don't fix things
by fixing the result.
You fix things by fixing the cause.
Fixing the result would be something like,
cleaning the puddle up every night.
But you didn't fix the source.
You didn't fix the cause of it
and then it's just going to come back again.
So the idea is: attack the
cause. Find the source
and attack that.
We just talked about
steps that have brought
about the problems in our lives,
starting with a tendency that we brought
into this life with us, with our mind,
to see things as coming from themselves.
And then that's going
to trigger this habit
of thinking that 'me' and
'mine' come from themselves.
And then that's going to
trigger this habit of liking
the things that seem good,
disliking the things that seem bad,
and then reacting to them
and responding to them.
Fighting for getting more of what I like,
fighting against people I don't like,
and then making more karma to
plant more seeds in my mind
to carry on into my next life
for the circle to continue again.
So we don't struggle
with, for example, money.
We don't struggle with money.
We don't struggle with current money.
We invest for future money
and that's all we do.
We don't fight.
We don't compete for current
existing amounts of money.
We don't do that in this system.
We plant the seeds that will grow money
a couple of weeks later
or couple of months later.
So we address the problem at the source
and we don't address the
problem at the result.
And that's the idea. So don't
forget "the sink thing."
Just to remind you, in this
chapter so far, we were supposed
to be covering five things.
Number one was, how do you get
into understanding emptiness?
And we finished that section.
There were five sections.
the third section — I'll
skip the second one —
was, how do you teach
someone about emptiness?
The fourth section was, what's
the essence of emptiness?
The fifth section is,
how do you put that into practice?
But the second section, which is what
we are going to cover today,
is called LUNG DANG 'GAL SPONG.
LUNG DANG 'GAL SPONG means,
"Hey, Nagarjuna! I like your ideas,
"they seem pretty interesting.
They are pretty persuasive,
"but aren't you contradicting
what Lord Buddha said?"
Because Lord Buddha did say
that things had a nature of their own.
He said they do have a nature of their own.
And he did.
So then Nagarjuna is
stuck in this position
which he was hard stuck into in which book?
"The Sixty Verses," which
Nick Lashaw is translating.
Like, you have to address the times
early in the Buddha's career when he said,
"Yes, things do have a
nature of their own."
And now we've got to talk about that.
So, here's Nagarjuna's response.
,BDAG GO ZHES KYANG BTAGS GYUR CING,
,BDAG MED CES KYANG BSTAN PAR GYUR,
,SANGS RGYAS RNAMS KYIS BDAG DANG NI,
,BDAG MED 'GA' MED CES KYANG BSTAN,
He says, "When you think about it,
"there's three options here."
What are the three?
,BDAG GO ZHES KYANG BTAGS,
Yes, the Buddha said, "There
is a self nature to things."
He did historically say,
"Things do have a self nature."
He did say that.
But the verb here is not
say. The verb here is 'BTAGS',
which means fantasize. (laughs)
So yes, Buddha did kind of fantasize
about a self nature.
There was a period in his life
when Buddha was fantasizing
about a self nature.
We'll see what this means later.
But then there was another
part of his life when
,BDAG MED CES KYANG BSTAN PAR GYUR,
But there was another part
of his life where he said,
"You know, things also
don't have a self nature."
So he qualified. Things also
don't have a self nature.
Then at the end, he said
,SANGS RGYAS RNAMS KYIS BDAG DANG NI,
,BDAG MED 'GA' MED CES KYANG BSTAN,
Later he said, "It's not true
that things have a self nature
and it's not true that they
don't have a self nature."
So we've got three options here.
In the early part of his
teaching career, Buddha said...
Buddha fantasized about a
self nature that was there.
Later he said, "You can take your choice,
take it or leave it: self
nature or no self nature."
He taught two options.
Then in the third...
Sorry. RNAMS KYIS BDAG DANG NI,
,BDAG MED 'GA' MED CES KYANG BSTAN,
He also taught... I'm sorry.
The third option was
it's not true that there is a self
and it's not true that there is no self.
Let me say it again. First
he said there is a self.
And he went like this, there is a "self".
Then he said, "You know
there is a way you can think
if there is a self or there is no self."
And then later he said,
"No, there is no self
and there's not no self."
So this Nagarjuna, he's being cute,
he really enjoys being cute.
So I thought it'd be
worth it to go through
these ideas separately, which
is going to slow us down
in a certain way.
But I'm not really excited.
Here is the commentary.
SANGS RGYAS RNAMS KYIS
NI MDO SDE 'GA' ZHIG TU
BDAG GO ZHES KYANG
BDAG YOD PAR BTAGS PAR
GYUR PA STE BSTAN PA LTAR GSUNGS
There was a time in the
Buddha's career when he said,
"Yes, there does exist a
self nature to things."
He said that.
First choice. Second choice:
YANG 'GA' ZHIG TU NI, RANG
RKYA THUB PA'I BDAG MED DO
Then he said KYANG BSTAN.
He said, "On top of
there being a self nature,
"there's also in some cases
a lack of a self nature."
He gave an option.
What was the lack of the
self nature he talked about?
In those days, it was the lower emptiness
of the lower schools, which just means
a self nature which is independent,
which doesn't depend on other things.
So the lower form of emptiness
is sort of like there's a driver.
You guys remember that?
RANG RKYA THUB PA'I RDZAS YOD KYIS STONG
Someone's in control. Someone
can be in current control.
You can get more money by
doing these things immediately
and not by being generous.
So he said there's no such
thing as that kind of money.
And finally: YANG 'GA' ZHIG
TU BDAG DANG BDAG MED PA 'GA'
YANG RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB PA MED DO
There is neither a self
nature nor no self nature
where both of those come
from their own side.
There is no self,
and there is no lack of a self nature,
but I'm only talking about ones
that come from their own side.
So that's three.
What's the goal of this section?
We're trying to explain why
Buddha seemed to have said
there was a self nature to things
and we end up saying
he were just saying different
things to different people.
Who did he say those things to?
RIM PA BZHIN DU BLO DMAN DAG LAS
'BRAS LA SKUR BA MI 'DEBS PA DANG
First of all, he did say
there was a a self nature
to people of lowest spiritual intellect
because he wanted to make sure
that they didn't discount karma
and its consequences.
So he wanted to say, "You
do have a self nature
"and things are going to come back to you
"if you do bad things."
So he was afraid if he
said there is no self,
people would go ahead and be naughty.
So he said, "No, that self exists.
"The one who gets back all
the trouble he gave to others,
"that one exists."
Because he wanted them to be good people.
Second: 'JIG LTA LHOD PA
He told other people,
"Well, you know, in some
ways there's a self
"and other ways there is no self."
And that's to help people
overcome the attitude
about the bottle of
water which is mistaken.
That 'me' and 'mine'
come from the outside.
Then, who did he give
the last explanation to?
Neither self nor no self
comes from themselves.
Who did he give that to?
ZAB MO'I DON RTOGS NUS PA'I GDUL BYA
He reserved that for students
who were extraordinarily
sensitive and were able
to get the deeper truth.
So yes, did he change
his message about self?
Yes.
Did he contradict himself about the self?
No.
Because it was very intentional.
He revealed different layers
of selflessness according to the capacity
of the students.
That covers that section.
Three kinds of me's. You've got it here?
I don't know... what was that.
We don't have to have that picture.
BSHAD TSUL GCIG LA
And I'm sorry to going
into all this detail
but it's just beautiful to me.
He says, "There is also a way in which
"you can explain these two differently."
Some people explain
these three differently.
He says, what?
He was trying to get along
with the Sāṃkhya.
He was trying to get along with followers
of the religion into which he was born.
And he said, "Of course
there's a self nature,
"it's inherent in all things.
"There is a big self who
creates all things."
He's trying not to freak out...
like Jesus among the
Jewish people or something.
He was trying to be cooperative
with who he grew up with.
That's one interpretation when it says
he did claim there was a self.
Second: RGYANG BAN PAS PHYI MAR
'GRO 'ONG BYED PA'I BDAG MED DO
And then there was a school
called the Charvakas,
who said there was nobody
to go on into a future life.
And he said, "No, that self there is."
You will take a future.
There is somebody who takes a future
life, trust me.
But he was just talking in that context.
SANGS RGYAS BCOM LDAN 'DAS
RNAMS KYIS NI BDAG DANG BDAG
MED PA 'GA' YANG RANG
BZHIN GYIS GRUB PA MED DO
And then finally, in his
ultimate presentation,
he said, "Уes, there is that 'me',
"yes, there is that 'mine',
but they do not come from
their own side." That's all.
Next section.
I like this section. This is pretty famous.
DON DAM PAR BRJOD MI NUS PA'I RGYU MTSAN
In the Vajrayogini sadhana:
BRJOD LAS 'DAS,
BRJOD DU MED PA
'Beyond words',
'Beyond description'
The reality of the world
is beyond all words.
And now that subject is going to come up.
DON DAM PAR BRJOD MI NUS PA'I RGYU MTSAN
Why is it that emptiness is
said to be indescribable?
If it's indescribable, why would we have
to study this long book
describing it? (laughs)
If emptiness is really indescribable,
why we got to do all this
hard work to describe it.
So Nagarjuna, thankfully - I
think sensitively for us -
he's going to say,
"Yes, we do say emptiness
is indescribable.
"Yes, we do say you can't
describe it in words,
"but that has a special meaning."
And here's the next verse:
,BRJOD PAR BYA BA LDOG PA STE,
,SEMS KYI SPYOD YUL LDOG PAS SO,
,MA SKYES PA DANG MA 'GAGS PA,
,CHOS NYID MYA NGAN 'DAS DANG MTSUNGS,
Then he says here:
,BRJOD PAR BYA BA LDOG PA STE,
Yeah, it cannot be immediately
expressed in words.
And usually, which we're
going to see later,
that means you can't sit down...
if you have seen emptiness directly,
and if a person says,
"Look, just sit down
with me for five minutes
and tell me what it is and I'll see it,"
and that's not possible.
So it cannot be put into
words in that sense.
You cannot inspire an
immediate direct perception
of emptiness in another person
just by talking about it.
So BRJOD PAR BYA BA LDOG PA
STE means it's not something
that could happen just
by talking about it.
,SEMS KYI SPYOD YUL LDOG PAS SO,
And that's because most people's
minds cannot conceptualize
what you're talking about.
You can sit down and describe emptiness
for hour after hour for
them, but they won't be able
to comprehend everything in such a way
that they would see emptiness directly,
within the next few hours.
That's usually not possible.
It did happen at the first
turning of the Wheel -
but those people were ready.
Why?
They had eaten their teacher.
(indistinct)
But we're not getting into that
and that's not a Buddhist practice.
,MA SKYES PA DANG MA 'GAGS PA,
,CHOS NYID MYA NGAN 'DAS DANG MTSUNGS,
In some respects, emptiness
is similar to nirvana.
And this is the highest
interpretation of nirvana.
We talk about it when we talk
about two kinds of nirvana:
one is called nirvana
with something left over,
and one is called nirvana
with nothing left over.
And the lower schools think
that first you achieve nirvana
with something left over -
meaning your physical body.
You permanently end your negative emotions,
and then later you die.
And you die with that pure state of mind,
but it's not like your body
blinks out or I guess it does, but anyway.
First, you clean up your mind,
and then you clean up your body.
So there is a period in your life
that you haven't died yet,
but you still have a
body that was created by
karma and kleshas.
And then the higher school
says, "No, no. That's not
what nirvana with remainder means."
Nirvana without remainder happens first
and that's the first...
those are the direct
perceptions of emptiness
where you are no longer
loaded up with the idea
that things come from their own side.
While you are seeing emptiness directly,
you are devoid of ideas
that things could come
from their own side.
During that less than twenty minutes,
you can't have a thought
that things are coming
from their own side.
Then you come out of the
direct perception of emptiness,
and for seven more lifetimes, on some level,
you still feel like things
come from their own side,
but you don't believe it.
So what he's referring to
here is that kind of nirvana
where for the twenty
minutes of direct perception
of emptiness, you no longer
have starting and stopping
in that sense.
You are free of normal starting
coming from its own side,
stopping from its own side, in that sense.
By the way, I can't avoid teaching
this paragraph because
Choney Lama refers to
the Diamond Cutter sutra.
And he says, "By the way"
and it starts with RDOR GCOD.
The paragraph starts with RDOR GCOD.
Maybe Tim will show to you.
By the way, he's doing an amazing job
just digging out pieces of
texts and showing them to us.
Let's read this together: RDOR
GCOD SOGS LAS SANGS RGYAS KYIS
CHOS GANG YANG BSTAN PA MED
"Look, I agree." "What?" "I agree that's what
the Diamond Cutter sutra says."
"What the Diamond Cutter sutra says?"
"The Diamond Cutter sutra says
"the Buddhas never teach the dharma."
GANG YANG BSTAN PA MED means
the Buddhas never teach any dharma.
And he say, "OK, look, I know that's what the
Diamond Cutter sutra says."
But, what it's saying is
he never teaches a dharma
which is coming from its own side.
Which means, when the
Buddha sat down in the
Jetavan Garden in Vaishali? No.
Śrāvastī.
When the Buddha sat down in
the Jetavan Garden at Śrāvastī
and taught the dharma - none
of it was coming from him.
The listeners who were there
had the seeds in their minds
to create a being who was
teaching them the path to freedom.
And the generations of
people, the twenty five...
Sorry, the hundred generations
of people after that
who read the Diamond Cutter
sutra, were writing the sutra
on the pages as they read.
That's coming from you.
The sutra came from you.
THA SNYAD DU NI SANGS RGYAS
KYIS BSTAN PAR 'DOD DGOS SO
He says, "Look, on a conventional
level, we have to say..."
THA SNYAD DU means
'on a conventional level', we have to say
the Buddha did teach the dharma.
That's not what this verse is about.
We're not denying that
the Buddha sat down
in the Jetavan Garden and
taught the Diamond Cutter sutra.
We're not saying that.
We're not saying he never taught it.
We're just saying that
nominally, conventionally speaking,
he taught it,
but if you look at it from
a karmic point of view,
you taught the Diamond Cutter sutra.
Anyone who ever heard it was teaching
the Diamond Cutter sutra.
That's starting a discussion
of using words to explain
a thing which is beyond words.
Of those five great, sexy
subjects, we've now reached
the third one, which is: DE KHO
NA NYID LA BKRI BA'I RIM PA
What a useful way to teach...
BKRI BA means
what's a useful way to guide people through
the concepts of emptiness.
BKRI BA means
what's a useful way to guide people
through these ideas.
And then he said,
,THAMS CAD YANG DAG YANG DAG MIN,
,YANG DAG YANG DAG MA YIN NYID,
,YANG DAG MIN MIN YANG DAG YIN,
,DE NI SANGS RGYAS RJES BSTAN PA'O,,
And he starts playing with the word
YANG DAG
Say YANG DAG. What's the Sanskrit?
Tathyaṃ, I guess,
tathyaṃ.
YANG DAG means 'pure', but the Sanskrit...
it seems like he's using tathyaṃ,
which means 'as it is'. tathya,
like Tathagata, for example. Anyway.
,THAMS CAD YANG DAG YANG DAG MIN,
I mean, if you read the
line, here's how it sounds:
"Everything is pure nothing is pure."
"Purity is not pure perfectly."
"That which is not pure is
the purity of what is not."
"That's what the Buddha taught." (laughs)
And the question is, I don't
know if we could go too much
into this - it'll take a long time.
Let's do it.
In what sense did the Buddha
teach the Diamond Cutter sutra?
RGYAL BAS 'JIG RTEN RJES SU
GZHUG PA'I CHED DU THOG MAR MA
RIG PAS BTAGS PA'I SNOD BCUD
THAMS CAD YANG DAG PA STE BDEN NO
ZHES GSUNGS SHING DE
LTAR 'DZIN DU GZHUG GO
In the beginning when the
Buddha first started to teach
in this world, he did
describe in the Abhidharma
what the world looks like,
how the world came into being.
And in that sense, he
said the world is pure.
But the word 'pure' here
in this verse means 'real'.
So pure here means real.
So did Buddha ever say the world was real?
Yes. When?
Like Abhidharma, in the third chapter.
He describes all the continents.
He describes the sun and the
moon. He describes the galaxy.
He describes the different
solar systems - it's all real.
Nowhere did he say all
this planets are not real.
In his first teaching.
,DE LA PHYIS 'DUS BYAS
'DI DAG SKAD CIG RE RE LA
'JIG PA'I GZHAN DU 'GYUR
BA YOD PAS YANG DAG PA
MIN NO ZHES BSTAN LA,
Then in his later teaching
he said, "But in a way
things are in constant flux,
"things never last for
more than a millisecond.
"And in that sense, they are impure."
They don't have purity
of being real for more
than a millisecond.
So let's call them unreal, in the
sense that they are fleeting
and they are changing instant by instant.
So did he ever say it was pure?
Yes.
Did he ever say it wasn't pure?
Did he ever it was real?
Yes.
Then after that - just after
that - did he say it wasn't real?
Yes.
Now, it's not finished!
DE NAS 'GA' ZHIG GI NGO BOR SNOD BCUD
'DI DAG YANG DAG PA DANG,'PHAGS
PA'I RJES THOB KYI YE SHES LA
BLTOS NAS YANG DAG PA MA YIN PA
Then he changed his story and said,
"For all you guys, the world is real,
"but not for an Arya."
For someone especially who is engaged
in the direct perception of
emptiness, the world is not real.
So far he said "real,"
then he said "unreal,"
because it's momentary,
and then he said "real and unreal"
depends on who you are,
depends on who's looking.
So far we've got real, unreal,
and real and unreal.
It's starting to make a
little more sense, right?
ZAB MO LA MOS PA'I NGO BOR
'DUS BYAS RNAMS YANG DAG MIN PA STE
SKAD CIG RE RE LA GZHAN DU
'GYUR PAR NGO BO NYID KYIS
GRUB PA YANG MIN LA,
YANG DAG PA STE SKAD CIG RE RE LA
GZHAN 'GYUR BA MED PA YANG MIN NO
ZHES GNYIS KA BKAG STE
Then those who were really
interested in emptiness,
he changed his story.
And he said, "Things that are
caused are not real." Why?
Because by the time they're real,
they change to something else. (laughs)
Things that are caused are
not real because by the time
they're real, they're not real anymore.
'GYUR PAR NGO BO NYID
KYIS GRUB PA YANG MIN LA,
YANG DAG PA STE
From another point of view, they are real.
SKAD CIG RE RE LA GZHAN 'GYUR BA MED PA
In the instant that they
are themselves, they are real.
But considered over
instants, they're unreal.
In the instant they're real.
Considered over a series of
instants, they are not real.
Changed his story.
Then Choney Lama makes a famous comment
that different presentations
of what reality means
to different levels of people is very much
a Buddhist tradition because
people are at different levels.
If you overwhelm a beginner student
with too heavy a presentation of emptiness,
you have mistaught them.
You are a bad teacher.
And Buddha is not a bad teacher.
So Buddha would modify the
presentation to fit the student,
even to the point of
saying things are not empty
when they are, if it
would help the student.
How are we doing on time?
I'm going to keep going, Tim, into
what we had called class four.
We're going to start studying...
I'd like to go back to the Sanskrit
and talk about some words that are useful
for studying the next section.
And the first one I'd like to talk about
is lakṣaṇa.
And I know Christina knows lakṣaṇa.
Lakṣaṇa means... it's a difficult word
and here it's going to mean
'typical characteristic', MTSAN NYID.
So lakṣaṇa means sign,
but in logic it has
totally different names.
It means kind of... what are the bright...
like you're selling somebody a new car,
what are the five lakṣaṇas?
Oh, it's got a 700-horsepower engine,
it's got six bold speakers...
These are lakṣaṇas,
qualities of the new car that stand out:
How do you say? Feature.
Excuse me. Bright shiny
features of the new car.
That's because lakṣ,
which means to mark a thing as special.
It comes from an Indo-European root leuk,
leuk, which means light or brightness.
I met a waiter... two days ago
I said, "What's your name?"
and he said, "Luke". I said,
"God, I was just studying
"this verbal root! Do you
know what your name means?"
And he says, "I have no idea."
And I said, "I think it
means shining person.
"You are a shining person."
He says, "I'll take it."
So leuk is the Indo-European root.
'Light' comes from that. That's
why there's a GH in light.
Brightness comes from that,
that's why there's a GH.
Rs and Ls are interchangeable, okay.
I worked in... I built an office in Bangkok.
We had three suppliers of gems,
lear gems, real gems, and rare gems.
Real gems, rare gems, and lear gems.
But when the receptionist called me
to tell me the salesman
was here, she said,
"Leal gems is here."
I said, "Which leal gems is here? Real?
I said, "Leal?" So R and L
are basically interchangeable
in Asian languages. And it's good.
So leuk is the root
and it actually it comes from ruc,
which means to shine,
and 'roach' comes from that.
So anyway, light and luster and lucid
are all cognates.
I chose the two signs
or bright shiny features, lakṣaṇa,
of the Buddha which I
would consider the most
important of the five that
he's going to present now.
And I'll give you the Sanskrit for those.
First one is śānta,
which means peace,
and it comes from a root śam.
And you know the word śanti,
and you know the word śamatha.
śamatha is ZHI GNAS,
which means to stay in peace.
Probably stha, śamastha.
If you are interested, most of the ancient
sh- roots used to be KSH.
Most of the ancient sh-
roots used to be KSH.
And those come into
western languages as QU.
So KSH is usually the real root
when it starts with SH,
and most often the KSH
comes into western languages
as QU, meaning quiet,
or also calm. And kṣanti
is patience.
So I want you to learn śānta.
Why?
Because it's going to
be one of the five great
lakṣaṇa of emptiness.
It's going to be one of the five great
selling points of emptiness.
Like selling a new Tesla car or something.
And another one I wanted
to teach you is actually
a lack of prapañca.
I like pañca, it means five.
It came into the word finger, five.
It came into the word fünf, in German,
which comes from pañc.
So fünf comes into English as five.
So it means five, but what
it means is... look at my hand.
It means, SPROS PA - the
verb means for light rays
to spread out.
We constantly see in those
tantric visualizations
the world is coming out
of Vajra Yogini's heart.
There's this SPROS PA of light.
SPROS PA means like
you take your hand and you go like that.
and that's pañca,
that's prapañca.
So pra- means forward, like
prow of a boat or proud,
and prapañca means the world is
a construct coming from you.
It's a finger coming from
you, but a different one,
five fingers. (laughs)
Anyway, I'm not going to talk about that.
I do have some self-control.
So we are going to go through the five...
these are the five shining
features of emptiness.
I think that would be
enough for this class today.
We'll go through the five features.
They're in the next verse.
,GZHAN LAS SHES MIN ZHI BA DANG,
,SPROS PA RNAMS KYIS MA SPROS PA,
,RNAM RTOG MED DON THA DAD MIN,
,DE NI DE NYID MTSAN NYID DO,
Here are the five
and I'll read them off to you.
Number one... and you can
leave that verse up, Tim.
GZHAN GYIS BSTAN PA TZAM LAS
DNGOS SU SHES PA MIN GYI
,GZHAN LAS SHES MIN means
emptiness is not something
you can see directly
by talking to someone directly.
No one can sit down and trigger
the direct perception of
emptiness in your mind
just by talking to you
about what they saw.
"So Geshe-la, you should never
have emptiness teachings."
No, no. That's not the point.
The point is, there's no
way for a person who has
seen emptiness, no matter how desperately
they might want to help you, they can't
force you to see emptiness directly
just by describing what they saw.
In that sense, it cannot be
communicated to another person directly.
That's what we mean by directly.
In the sense that if I explain it to you
for ten minutes suddenly you see it.
That's not going to happen.
Does that mean we
shouldn't study emptiness?
Duh, no.
Of course you have to.
So that's the first quality of emptiness.
,GZHAN LAS SHES MIN
Not something you could
directly or immediately
learn from another person.
ZHI BA means but it is a kind of peace.
And it's not that you sit
down and feel peaceful.
That's not what it means.
'Peace' means...
There's a joke, I mean the Sanskrit root
śam, śāntiḥ also refers
to 'wiping something out',
like stopping it completely, put to rest,
rest in peace.
Rest in peace, meaning 'dead', 'finished'.
So whenever you see śāntiḥ in Sanskrit,
just be aware it also refers
to 'putting out a fire',
the same word means putting out a fire.
So making the fire leave existence.
So that is what it means here.
What fire does emptiness put out?
The perception that the
bottle is coming from itself.
A bottle that could come
from itself is permanently
shut down, śāntiḥ.
That's śāntiḥ, that's peace.
So it doesn't mean the Eagle's
song "Peaceful easy feeling."
It's not that at all.
It's rather like putting out a car fire
and saving the inhabitant of the car.
Number three: ,SPROS
PA RNAMS KYIS MA SPROS PA,
No prapañca, no...
And here you have to call it constructs.
No stories that
you make up in your head.
Emptiness is free of stories
that you make up in your head.
This is called elaborations.
Some translators call it elaboration.
I like to call it constructs.
It means stuff made up in your head.
Emptiness is free and he says specifically
verbal elaborations or verbal constructs.
It's not something you can
elaborate on with words
and see it directly. That's
not going to happen.
It's related to the first one.
The fourth one was RNAM RTOG MED,
which means no normal thought.
Unthinkable with normal
thought. What? Emptiness. Why?
When your mind is thinking normal thoughts,
you can not see emptiness directly.
So if there's a flow of
normal thoughts in your
mind, it will stop the
perception of emptiness.
And this refers to a contradiction,
inherent contradiction.
I give you, day after day, a
description of how the bottle
is not coming from its own side.
While I'm giving you that description,
you are desperately holding to the idea
that it's coming from the bottle.
When I hold the bottle
up to tell you why it's
not coming from the bottle, you are seeing
it as coming from the
bottle until I put it down.
And it's one of the big
contradictions of teaching
emptiness.
Even as you hold the pen up
and explain why it's
not coming from itself,
there's no one in the
audience who doesn't feel
that it's coming from itself.
It's just the way that it is.
If you tell him ten thousand times,
you might have some hope.
But the first ten thousand times,
when they see the pen,
they automatically think
it's coming from itself,
even as you explain how
it's not coming itself.
And that's what he's talking about here.
Normal flow of thought is interrupted.
Number five:
CHOS THAMS CAD KYI DE KHO
NA NYID RIGS MTSUNGS PAS
DON THA DAD PA MIN PA STE
When we explain the diamond
in the Diamond Cutter sutra,
we often talk about
this particular quality
of emptiness, which is that all objects
have their own emptiness.
All objects are devoid
of not coming from you.
All objects in the universe are devoid
All husbands in the kitchen are empty
of not coming from you.
Which is to say, all
husbands in the kitchen
are coming from you.
That is their dependent origination.
But to state it emptiness-way:
no husband in the kitchen
is not coming from you.
CHOS THAMS CAD KYI DE KHO
NA NYID RIGS MTSUNGS PAS
In that sense, all objects in the universe
are totally equal.
So Buddha's saying constantly - equanimity,
but there is a higher...
treat all the people the same,
see all the people the same,
but there's a higher form of equanimity,
which we don't talk about very often,
which is that you should
see all objects as equal
in that they are coming equally from you.
They all share a certain quality
that they are coming from you.
And there's many stories
in scripture of a
teacher handing a student
a little piece of dog
poop, or a piece of meat,
or glass of wine,
and saying, "Take a drink or taste it."
And the student will say,
"No! It's poo-poo."
Lama Pelma used to do it.
The student said, "I'm
totally into emptiness."
She said, "Okay, eat the poo-poo then."
And some brave students tried.
By the way, I'm not to recommending that.
I'm not teaching that. I'm
not asking you to do that.
And it's a pity I have to repeat that.
But the point is
dog poo-poo does have its own emptiness.
And from that point of
view, it might be worth it
to taste dog poo-poo every once in a while,
just so you can say,
"This does have
"the same quality as emptiness."
Or "This does have the same quality
"as Nagarjuna's great Wisdom."
They all share a certain high quality
in that they don't come from themselves.
So the reason these tantric yogis
why they do strange things
is to remind themselves,
like in tasting poo-poo,
which I don't recommend
and I'm not teaching that.
The only way you could
do it, is if you were
reflecting on something deeper:
(laughs)
this, too, is not not coming from you.
So those are the five great qualities.
Those are the five great lakṣaṇa
of emptiness,
and they're very, very beautiful.
And these are traditionally
taught by Nagarjuna.
Next, we're going to
get into how the world
might misunderstand emptiness.
That's the next topic
that we'll be covering
in the next class from
the eighteenth chapter,
tenth verse.
All right, see you then.
We're going slower than
I expected, but we'll just
have more Nagarjuna classes.
Thank you, guys. Thank you, Tim.